Guide to the Cindy Bonner Papers
The Wittliff Collections
Cindy Bonner Papers
1983-1999
The Wittliff Collections
Bonner, Cindy, 1953-
SWWC.053
12 boxes
6 Linear Feet
The Cindy Bonner papers document the writing and editing process of her novels and short stories, including research notes, annotated drafts, proofs, and correspondence, dating from 1983-1999.
Source of Acquisition
Gifts of Bonner since 1994.
Biographical Notes
Cindy Bonner was born June 14, 1953, in Corpus Christi, Texas. She attended University of Southern Mississippi (1971-73), and San Antonio College (1979). She won Honorable Mention, Roberts Awards, 1989, and third place for a short story, Byliners Contest, 1990. Her first novel, Lily (1992), was a finalist for the Western Writers of America's Pipe Bearer's Award. Her novels have been listed as "Best Books" by the American Library Association and have been translated into Spanish and German. Her most recent novel, Right from Wrong, won the Pen Texas Award in 1997.
In addition to raising two children, Ms. Bonner has worked in various professions, including as a yoga teacher, computer operator, real estate manager of a blues/rock band, and writer. She stated, "In 1982, with the encouragement of my husband, I bought a spiral notebook and began to teach myself to write… the hard way, through trial and error and a tidal wave of rejection letters. It is my goal to write fiction that someone, somewhere, will still be reading in one hundred years from now," (Contemporary Authors, 1999). Ms. Bonner currently lives and writes full-time in Yorktown, Texas.
Scope and Contents
The Cindy Bonner papers document the writing and editing process of her novels and short stories. The collection includes research notes, annotated drafts, proofs, and correspondence, dating from 1983-1999. The collection is arranged in three series: Works, Correspondence, and Artifacts.
Series I: Works (1986-1999) documents the writing and editing process of Bonner's four published novels, Lily, Looking After Lily, The Passion of Dellie O'Barr, and Right from Wrong. This series also includes the unpublished novel "Flossie/War Dreams" and seven short stories. Formats include research notes, annotated drafts, proofs, and correspondence.
Series 2: Correspondence (1983-1993) relates to Bonner's writing career and includes letters of acceptance and rejection, and dialogue with literary agents. And Series 3: Artifacts (undated) includes one toy pencil that reads, "I'm a Big Time Writer." The toy was given to Bonner by her son and remained on her desk for five years.
Women authors, Texan; Literature; Historical fiction; Bonner, Cindy, 1953-
- Novels, 1991-1999
  Scope and Contents
  Series I: Novels (1991-1999) documents the writing and editing process of Bonner's four published novels, Lily, Looking After Lily, The Passion of Dellie O'Barr, and Right from Wrong. This series also includesthe unpublished novel "Flossie/War Dreams." Formats include research notes, annotated drafts, proofs, and correspondence.
  - Lily, 1992
    - Handwritten draft (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Outline (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Research (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - First Draft "McDade" (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
    - Original "McDade" (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
    - "McDade edited," with editor's marks (Box 1, Folder 8, Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Copy edited Lily (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - Edited page proofs (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Annotated page proofs (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Final Page Proofs (Box 3, Folder 2-3)
    - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Publicity (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Looking After Lily, 1994
    - Research (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - "First First Draft" (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - First Draft (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - Draft with December 1992 journal entry (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - "Clean Draft" (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    - "First Edit" (Box 4, Folder 6, Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Annotated typescript (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
    - "Copy Edit" (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
    - Publicity (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - The Passion of Dellie O'Barr, 1996
    - Annotated typescript #1 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
    - Annotated typescript #2 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    - Annotated typescript #3 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
    - Page Proofs (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - Right from Wrong, 1999
    - Orignial typescript as submitted to editor (Box 7, Folder 3-4)
    - Rejected Version (Box 7, Folder 5, Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Annotated typescript #1 (Box 8, Folder 2-3)
    - Annotated typescript #2 (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
    - Annotated page proofs (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
    - Publicity (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Publicity and promotional materials (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Flossie/War Dreams
    - Flossie typescript (Box 9, Folder 4-5)
    - War Dream typescript (Box 9, Folder 6, Box 10, Folder 1)
- Short Stories, 1986-1993
  Series II: Short Stories (1986-1999)documents the writng porcess of seven short stories. Formats include drafts and correspondence.
  - "Hatching Eggs" drafts and correspondence, 1988-1993 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - "Library Books", 1987-1992 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - "Pendejo" drafts and correspondence, 1986-1987 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - "Perfect Pitch", 1987-1989 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - "Starving Artist", 1988-1992 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - "Weekends and Summers", 1987 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - "Worms", 1989 (Box 11, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1983-1993
  Series III Correspondence (1983-1993)relates to Bonner's writing career and includes letters of acceptance and rejection, and dialogue with literary agents.
  - Correspondence, 1983-1993 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Artifacts
  Series 3: Artifacts (undated) includes one toy pencil thatreads,"I'm a Big Time Writer." The toy was given to Bonner by her son and remained on her desk for five years.
  - Toy pencil which reads, "I'm a Big Time Writer," given to Bonner by her son, includes note describing item (Box 12, Folder 1)